Miller, David P. Arbitration Papers 6338
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
David P. Miller Arbitration Papers
1948-1979
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Miller, David P.
American Arbitration Association (AAA)
National Academy of Arbitrators (NAA)
6338
7.5 cubic feet
7.5 linear ft.
Collective labor agreements.
7654362
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, April 26, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, March 07, 2016
Biographical / Historical
David P. Miller was born in Cleveland, Ohio on June 21, 1919. After serving nearly five years in the US Army during World War II he received a BS from the University of Arizona in 1948. This degree was followed by an MBA from the University of California at Berkeley in 1950.
After a brief employment by the US Department of Labor as a wage economist in 1950 Miller became an Impartial Manager for the Ford-UAW retirement board, a position he held until his death. He was also an Associate Umpire for Ford and the UAW from 1952 to 1959, and the Ad Hoc S.U.B. Plan Chairman from 1958 on. Unfortunately the Ford-UAW representatives decided not to cite Associate Umpire awards in their arbitrations, only Umpire awards. This meant that Miller's roughly 1,000 memorandum decisions never served as precedents in later cases.
Miller served as an Umpire and Arbitrator for US Steel and the United Steelworkers of America from 1962 on. He was also an Umpire for the Aluminum Company of America (ALCO) and the Aluminum Workers International Union (1965 on), the Budd Company and the UAW (1971 on), and the Borroughs Corporation and the UAW (1964-1965). By his estimate he wrote about 2,000 Umpire decisions.
His ad hoc arbitration dealt mostly with newspaper and communication workers. Some of the unions involved were the CWA, OCAW, Pressmen, Typographers, IBEW, and Machinists. By his estimate he wrote about 1,000 ad hoc decisions.
Miller was a member and on the arbitration panels of the American Academy of Arbitrators and the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service. He was a member of the Industrial Relations Research Association, the Society of Professionals in Dispute Resolution (SPIDR), and the National Academy of Arbitrators (NAA). Miller served the NAA in several capacities: Executive Secretary (1962-1968), member of the Board of Governors (1968-1971), Vice-President (1972-1973), President-Elect (1973-1974), and President (1974-1975).
David P. Miller died of a heart attack, in Detroit, Michigan, on March 22, 1975 at the age of 55.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6338 MB: David P. Miller Memorabilia 6338 P: David P. Miller Photographs
Arrangement
Series Personal
Series Ford Motor Company and United Auto Workers
Series General David Miller Arbitrations
Series Transit Arbitrations
Series National Academy of Arbitrators (NAA) Presidents Files
Arbitration, Industrial; Collective labor agreements; Miller, David P.; Aluminum Company of America; Aluminum Workers International Union; Borroughs Corporation; Budd Company; Communications Workers of America; Ford Motor Company; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers; International Typographical Union; International Union of Machinists and Blacksmiths of the U.S.A.; International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America; Oil, Chemical, and Atomic Workers International Union; United States Steel Corporation; United Steelworkers of America
7654362
- Series Personal
  - University of California, Business Administration 193b-Industrial Diplomacy, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - University of California-Labor Law 155, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - University of California Business Administration 297: The California State Conciliation Service (Copy 1), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - University of California Business Administration 297: The California State Conciliation Service (Copy 2), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - University of California Econ 252: "Some Aspects of Labour's Political Action in Britain Since 1945", 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - NAA Membership, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Harry Schulman & Saul Wallen Obituary, 1955-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - News clipping "Welfare, Pension, Grew like Topsy", 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Arbitration Statements, 1959-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Arbitration Panel Appointments, 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Arbitration Contracts, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Contact Index Cards (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Problems of the Arbitration Profession (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Expedited Arbitration (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Telephone" Arbitration (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - A suggested "Supplementary" Arbitration Procedure (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Notes (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Arbitration Billing Statements, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Wage Evaluation Talk Aluminum Workers International Union, Annual Meeting, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Society of Professionals in Dispute Resolution membership, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - William B. Gould: The Public Interest and the Role of the Neutral in Equal Opportunity Laws & Programs, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - ALCOA-AWIU Meeting, Pittsburgh, PA, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Scope and Contents
    March 5-7
  - US Steel-United Steel Workers of America Board of Arbitration Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - ALCOA-AWIU Meeting, Miami, Florida, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    February 22-24
  - ALCOA-AWIU St. Louis, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    March 25-29
  - ALCOA-AWIU, Pittsburgh, PA, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    June 10-12
  - ALCOA-Warrick, St. Louis, MO, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    July 9-10
  - ALCOA-AWIU & NAA Pittsburgh PA & Annapolis, Maryland, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    September 11-14
  - Aluminum Workers, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Aluminum Workers International Union speech (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Public Sector Collective Bargaining-Industrial Relations Research Association, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Practice, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Biography for Ford-UAW Umpire Position, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Detroit Newspapers Publishers, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Get Well" Wishes, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Obituaries, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Condolences to Mrs. Miller (Folder 1 of 2), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Condolences to Mrs. Miller (Folder 2 of 2), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Ben Rathbun: Will Success Ruin the Arbitrators?, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Hazel Miller NAA Annual Meeting, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Colorado Springs Med Ev. Talk, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Open Reel Audio Tape
- Series Ford Motor Company and United Auto Workers
  - Ford-UAW Benefits Schedule (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ford Labor Relations Staff (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ford-UAW Notes for talk on Retirement (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ford-UAW Pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ford-UAW: What's What when you Retire, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Highlights of UAW-Ford Agreement, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Supplemental Unemployment Benefit Plan Arbitrations, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ford-UAW Agreements, 1961-1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Ford-UAW Retirement Plan Highlights, 1953-1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ford-UAW Retirement Board Minutes, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ford-UAW Retirement Board Salary, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ford Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ford-UAW Associate Umpire Decisions 1-200, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    David P. Miller, Umpire
  - Ford-UAW Associate Umpire Decisions 201-400, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Ford-UAW Associate Umpire Decisions 401-600, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Ford-UAW Associate Umpire Decisions 601-800, 1956-1947 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Ford-UAW Associate Umpire Decisions 801-999, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Series General David Miller Arbitrations
  - Arbitration Awards and Opinions Vol.1, 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Arbitration Awards and Opinions Vol.2, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Arbitration Awards and Opinions Vol.3, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Arbitration Awards and Opinions Vol.4, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Arbitration Awards and Opinions Vol.5, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Arbitration Awards and Opinions Vol.6, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Arbitration Awards Vol.7, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Arbitration Awards Vol.8, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Arbitration Awards Vol.9, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Arbitration Awards Vol.10, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Arbitration Awards Vol.11, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Arbitration Awards Vol.12, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Arbitration Awards Vol.13, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Arbitration Awards Vol.13 (Home Set), 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Arbitration Awards Vol.14 (Home Set), 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Arbitration Awards Vol.15 (Home Set), 1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Arbitration Awards Vol.16 (Home Set), 1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Arbitration Awards Vol.17 (Home Set), 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Arbitration Awards Vol.18 (Home Set), 1972 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Arbitration Awards Vol.19, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Budd-UAW Arbitrations, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Detroit Bartender's Union Local 562 Arbitration, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Detroit Typographical Union Local 18-Detrot Free Press Arbitrations, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Baltimore Newspaper Web Pressmen's Union, Local 31 - A.S. Abell Company, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Aluminum Company of America (ALCOA)-Aluminum Workers International Union (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - United Steelworkers of American Arbitration, 1968-1979 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - UAW Arbitration, 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Baseball File, 1973-1975 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series Transit Arbitrations
  - Transit Operating Division/MTC and Amalgamated Transit Union, Transcript of Proceedings, Minneapolis, MN, Vol.1, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    June 13-16
  - Transit Operating Division/MTC and Amalgamated Transit Union, Transcript of Proceedings, Minneapolis, MN, Vol.2, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Transit Operating Division/MTC and Amalgamated Transit Union, Transcript of Proceedings, Minneapolis, MN, Vol.3, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Transit Operating Division/MTC and Amalgamated Transit Union, Transcript of Proceedings, Minneapolis, MN, Vol.4, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Transit Operating Division/MTC and Amalgamated Transit Union, Brief on Behalf of the Commission, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    July 12
  - Transit Operating Division/MTC and Amalgamated Transit Union-Company Exhibits. Minneapolis, MN, (Folder 1 of 4), 1972 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Transit Operating Division/MTC and Amalgamated Transit Union-Company Exhibits. Minneapolis, MN, (Folder 2 of 4), 1972 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Transit Operating Division/MTC and Amalgamated Transit Union-Company Exhibits. Minneapolis, MN, (Folder 3 of 4), 1972 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Transit Operating Division/MTC and Amalgamated Transit Union-Company Exhibits. Minneapolis, MN, (Folder 4 of 4), 1972 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Transit Operating Division/MTC and Amalgamated Transit Union-Union Exhibits. Minneapolis, MN, (Folder 1 of 2), 1972 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Transit Operating Division/MTC and Amalgamated Transit Union-Union Exhibits. Minneapolis, MN, (Folder 2 of 2), 1972 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Transit Operating Division/MTC and Amalgamated Transit Union-Correspondence Minneapolis, MN, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Transit Operating Division/MTC and Amalgamated Transit Union-Notes. Minneapolis, MN, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-Transcript of Proceedings, Baltimore, MD. Vol.1, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-Transcript of Proceedings, Baltimore, MD. Vol.2, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-Transcript of Proceedings, Baltimore, MD. Vol.3, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-Transcript of Proceedings, Baltimore, MD. Vol.4, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-Transcript of Proceedings, Baltimore, MD. Vol.5, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-Transcript of Proceedings, Baltimore, MD. Vol.6, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-Transcript of Proceedings, Baltimore, MD. Vol.7, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-Arbitration, Baltimore, MD., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-Joint Exhibits, Baltimore, MD., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-Non-Critical Union Pension Exhibits, Baltimore, MD., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-MTA Non-Critical Wage Exhibits, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-Union exhibits (Folder 1 of 2), Baltimore, MD., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-Union exhibits (Folder 2 of 2), Baltimore, MD., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-Exhibits 122-194, Baltimore, MD., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-Exhibits 195-241, Baltimore, MD., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-Notes, Baltimore, MD., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-From Binder Labeled "Pensions" (Folder 1 of 2), Baltimore, MD., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-From Binder Labeled "Pensions" (Folder 2 of 2), Baltimore, MD., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-From Binder Labeled MTA/TU Proposals, Folder 1 of 2, Baltimore, MD., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Mass Transit Administration, Amalgamated Transit Union-From Binder Labeled MTA/TU Proposals, Folder 2 of 2, Baltimore, MD., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - National Academy of Arbitrators Constitution and Bylaws, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Series National Academy of Arbitrators (NAA) Presidents Files
  - NAA Member Directories, 1959-1975 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - NAA Committee on Committees, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - NAA General Correspondence, 1965-1975 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - NAA Foreign Correspondence, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - NAA Misc. Correspondence, "No Replies", 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - NAA Eli Rock Correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - NAA Correspondence, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    May 9, 1974 - August 9, 1974
  - NAA Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    August 12, 1974 - March 5, 1975
  - NAA Board of Governors, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - NAA Appointments, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - NAA Department of Labor Proposal, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - NAA Lewis Gill, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - NAA Insurance, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - NAA Legal Affairs, 1972-1974 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - NAA Thomas McDermott-"Training Program for Neutrals", 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - NAA Regional Activities, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - NAA Annual Volume, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - NAA The Chronicle, 1974-1978 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - NAA Newsletter, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - NAA Committee of Law and legislation draft papers, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - NAA Membership Committee, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - NAA Nominations Committee, 1972-1975 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - NAA Committee on Public Employment (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - NAA Committee on Railway Adjustment, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - NAA Re-Examination Committee, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - NAA 27th Annual Meeting, Kansas City, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - NAA Secretary's Reports, Minutes, Treasurers Reports, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - NAA 28th Annual Meeting, Cerromar Arrangements, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - NAA 28th Annual Meeting, Program Committee, Cerromar, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - NAA 28th Annual Meeting, Cerromar, PR. Registration D.P. Miller, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - NAA 32nd Annual Meeting. Venue, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    1979, Dertoit, MI
  - NAA Canadian Regional Meeting, Qubec, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - NAA 2nd Annual Inter-Regional Conference, Angola, IN, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - NAA 22nd Annual BNA Conference, Atlanta, GA, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - NAA Tri-Regional Meeting Chicago, IL., 1974 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Richard Mittenthal-"Joys of Being an Arbitrator", 1979 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - NAA Arbitration: A management approach seminar, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - NAA Handwritten Notes (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - NAA Code of Ethics Pamphlets, 1957-1964 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - NAA Ethics Committee (Folder 1 of 2), 1972-1974 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - NAA Ethics Committee (Folder 2 of 2), 1972-1974 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - NAA Ethics Committee Mittenthal, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - NAA Ethics Committee Procedures (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - NAA Ethics Code, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - NAA Ethics Code, Draft, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - NAA Ethics Code, Final Draft, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 8)